[UNCLE] The nomads attacked,
defeating our militia.
Without our forces,
it will be impossible
to prevent them
from entering the city.
When they arrive,
there'll be pillaging.
So, we'll need to hide our food
and valuables before then.
[Zumurrud grunts] We won't get
too much down here.
[ANIS] Mm...
[smirks]
[BOTH] Uh?
[both exclaim]
I'll lead my sons
to the mountains,
and we shall take shelter there.
Yes, good idea.
For right now,
you and Sitara
need to hide down in the cellar.
We will come back in three days.
Sitara, I leave Ms. Fatima
in your hands.
Sure! I'll keep her safe!
And we'll be seeing you soon.
-Till then...
-You two take care!
[ANIS] Times like these bring me
back to my childhood.
We fled our city more times
than I can count.
[ZUMURRUD]
You should at least feel
a little worried about all this!
[ANIS] I suppose so.
[SITARA] Mistress,
why don't you have some dates?
[FATIMA]
That sounds nice. Thank you.
In this cellar,
it feels as though the world
has come to a complete stop.
I can see the outside light
through here.
It has already come and gone
three times now.
So, that should mean Uncle
and the others
will be coming to get us soon.
But still...
If it takes them
a little longer,
thanks to all their
preparations,
we'll have plenty of supplies
to last us!
And your books
are safe here, too!
You're right.
Thank you, Sitara.
Having you with me
keeps my spirits high.
I haven't done anything!
Uh...
Come to think of it.
I wonder
if the nomads have read
about Euclid's
different theorems.
I'm not sure.
That said, I mustn't lose
a single volume.
My husband spent
his life collecting them.
[Sitara exclaims]
Yes, you're right.
[Fatima chuckles]
Sitara, I'm curious.
You care for Muhammad,
don't you?
[Sitara gasps, stutters]
Yes. I think highly of him.
There can't be many people
in the world
who are as intelligent.
[Fatima chuckles softly]
The boy takes after his father.
Bridling at the restrictions
of conservative theology.
But still...
The more he walks
his own path in life,
the more objections
and resistance he will face.
In such times,
there will be only one person
able to comfort him.
Sitara, that would be you.
[Sitara gasps]
I want you to serve my son.
As a human unto yourself.
♪
[Sitara breathes softly]
[Fatima chuckles]
[Sitara breathes shakily]
I will.
-[footsteps]
-[thumping]
[SITARA AND FATIMA] Uh?
[FATIMA] It's my brother
and the girls.
We can finally come out.
[SITARA] Yes!
[BOTH] Hm.
[both grunt]
[Sitara gasps]
[Fatima exhales]
[SITARA] Uh?
[Sitara breathes uneasily]
[footsteps approaching]
[TOLUI] Ah...
[♪ opening theme song playing]
[Sitara grunts]
[gasps]
I thank you, Sitara.
[SITARA] Of course.
-Stand back.
-[Sitara gasps]
[Sitara grunts]
Sitara.
Don't offer resistance.
Yes...
Mistress.
[SHIRA] Uh?
[Shira chuckles]
[thudding]
[Sitara and Fatima
breathe uneasily]
[Fatima breathes shakily]
[Fatima, in English]
No! Not that book!
[laughs]
[Fatima breathes shakily]
[grunts]
[in English] "Whether they are
a man or woman,
cut off the hands of thieves
as punishment for the awful deed
they have done!"
-Sitara!
-It's not right.
That book doesn't belong to you,
so you must give it back!
[in English] My Master says
you are not to call him a thief.
"Everything on this..."
[SITARA] This boy understands
our language.
"...The Genghis Khan."
[both gasp]
[Sitara trembles]
-[Shira breathes shakily]
-[Fatima, in English] No!
[Fatima screams, echoes]
[Sitara gasps]
[SITARA] Uh...
-Mistress?
-[Fatima breathes weakly]
Don't you...
dare touch...
[breathes shakily]
my beloved daughter.
[Sitara whimpers]
Mistress?
Mistress? Mistress! [cries]
[wails]
♪
[Sitara gasps softly]
[Sitara breathes shakily]
[SITARA] Uh?
[ANIS] Uh?
Sitara?
[Zumurrud gasps]
[Anis gasps]
[ANIS] Oh, you're alive.
Are you hurt?
Ms. Anis, I... I, uh...
[tearfully]
I didn't keep my promise...
to keep the Mistress safe.
-The Mistress is...
-[Sitara cries]
[ANIS] Oh...
They had captured us
as we were all making our way
up to the mountains.
[Zumurrud and Anis laugh]
[both gasp]
[ANIS] After that, we were
divided into smaller groups.
Women, children,
and skilled craftsmen.
Then, the men and the elderly
were rounded up
and taken away somewhere.
We haven't seen Uncle since.
And then...
[men groaning]
[Zumurrud cries] Mikhail!
[cries] Mikhail!
[SITARA] Oh, no.
Ms. Zumurrud...
[cries]
[in English] Please, you have to
stop crying. [shushes]
Now be a good baby.
Ms. Zumurrud...
can you stand?
-[horse neighs]
-[grunting]
[ANIS] Have you got her?
[SITARA] Uh?
I know him.
He's the ironmonger who fixed
that water basin for us.
We must find Uncle
and the others soon!
[woman screaming]
[gasps] Hasan! Hasan!
[woman groans]
[SOLDIER] Chuu!
[SITARA (ADULT)] Their fear
of these mysterious men
spurred Sitara and the others
forward into the vast wasteland.
[SITARA] This year,
the month of Safar
still feels a little chilly,
so the water is cold.
Although...
when the sun is out,
I see the rose buds
are already starting to swell.
As Anis and I are doing
our chores...
[CHILDREN]
"In the mighty name of Allah,
the Most Gracious..."
[SITARA] We can hear
Uncle's students
practicing their
recitation together.
-How adorable.
-[Sitara chuckles]
It reminds me
of when I first came out here!
[exclaims]
They've returned!
Hello, Mistress, welcome home!
So how was the bazaar today?
Thanks to Zumurrud,
I found quite a few
bargains there.
That's because I'm always
at your service.
[Fatima laughs] That's true.
Sitara, you'll have to
come with us next time.
Great!
By the way, I just sent a letter
off to Nishapur.
As the roses bloom,
a reply might arrive.
[Sitara exclaims]
[SITARA] After Safar comes
the month of Rabi' al-Awwal,
when the roses bloom.
At least, when they should have.
[Sitara cries]
[ANIS] Zumurrud, you must eat
to keep up your energy.
[Zumurrud groans]
And you as well.
So, go on then.
[SITARA] You have it, Ms. Anis.
[Anis exhales]
[ANIS] Thank you.
But this share here
is all yours.
Hey, tell me.
Do you remember when I said
slaves don't get
to decide things for themselves?
[SITARA] Yes.
Viewed in another way,
it means slaves aren't
responsible for things, either.
For instance, even if one
were to commit a crime,
their punishment is only half
that of somebody who's free.
[Sitara gasps softly]
[ANIS] I suppose
you could say they think
we aren't capable of answering
for our own behavior.
When it comes to the Mistress,
you mustn't decide for yourself
whether you're
accountable or not.
[Sitara cries]
Then who decides it?
There's no one left who can!
The Mistress or Uncle.
They're both... [cries]
That's true.
Wait,
there is still one person
who's in Nishapur.
[Sitara breathes shakily]
Yes, that's right.
[Anis chuckles]
Master Muhammad's out there.
He's still alive!
[ANIS] That's right.
So, you see then.
We still have one person left.
[Sitara breathes shakily]
[Anis chuckles softly]
We... [cries]
We do! [cries]
[Zumurrud cries]
[SITARA (ADULT)] Soon...
the prisoners continued
moving eastward.
Day after day,
they traveled...
...threading between mountains,
crossing rivers.
And then, just as Safar
was ending...
[Sitara (adult), in English]
The caravan came to a stop,
arriving at a group of tents.
Pitched in a place
called Taloqan.
[sheep bleating]
[GIRL] Uh?
[SITARA] There are people here
who aren't soldiers.
Could this be their city?
[CRAFTSMAN] Excuse me,
where do you all hail from?
[all gasp]
From Tus.
[craftsman breathes uneasily]
[CRAFTSMAN] You mean
they even conquered Tus?
[breathes uneasily]
Where are you from?
They spared us.
After we identified ourselves
as skilled craftsmen,
they brought us down here...
[exhales]
...from Nishapur.
[Sitara gasps]
♪
[CRAFTSMAN] After we learned
the nomads were approaching,
we fortified our defenses.
Then at the very moment
they descended upon us,
a single arrow fired
from the ramparts.
Found its mark and struck down
their commander.
And in retaliation
for that one arrow,
the city of Nishapur was
completely burned to the ground!
[Craftsman, in English]
We skilled craftsmen
are the only people
who survived.
The others,
even our children were...
[Sitara gasps softly]
[SITARA] Master Muhammad
was in Nishapur.
Can't be...
[Zumurrud grunts]
[all gasp]
[ANIS] Zumurrud!
[SITARA] Ms. Zumurrud!
[Zumurrud groans]
Mikhail...
Mikhail.
Uh?
Zumurrud.
[ZUMURRUD] The setting sun.
It's so bright,
isn't it, Mikhail?
-[waves lapping]
-[birds screeching]
[ZUMURRUD] And so beautiful.
-[Sitara and Anis gasp]
-[SITARA] Ms. Zumurrud!
[ANIS] Please, no!
Don't leave us!
I'm begging of you!
[both crying]
[SITARA] Ms. Zumurrud
came from a distant land
where she could watch the sea!
She served the mistress
longer than any of us.
Did she want to return
there the whole time?
Did she miss her family
the whole time?
[Sitara cries]
[ANIS] We must give her
a proper burial at least.
And reunite her
with her brother.
[SITARA] "Indeed.
We all belong to Allah."
[ALL] "And indeed,
to Him we shall return."
[Sitara snores]
Now there is no joy.
-[birds chirping]
-[flock bleating]
[WOMAN 1] Poor thing.
[WOMAN 2] What happened?
[Sitara gasps]
Excuse me.
[gasps]
[WOMAN 1] She lunged
at a soldier who was walking by.
[Sitara gasps]
And then he just
struck her down.
[WOMAN 2] How dreadful!
So why is everyone just...
[CRAFTSMAN]
Peace be upon her soul.
[SITARA]
She decided for herself.
Rather than becoming a slave
to the nomads
for the rest of her life,
Ms. Anis wanted to die
while she was still a slave
to her Tus family.
I know.
If I keep walking
straight ahead,
maybe someone will shoot
an arrow into me.
[SHIRA] Wait!
[Sitara gasps]
[SITARA] It's that boy.
[Sitara grunting]
[Shira grunts]
It's not... it's not like that!
-Hey, listen!
-[Sitara crying]
You wanna get that book back,
don't you?
[Sitara gasps softly]
[♪ closing theme song playing]
[SITARA (ADULT)] Next time,
"An Undying Flame."